Finding Aid for Older Women's League. Michigan Chapter. Records 1982-2002.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Older Women's League. Michigan Chapter. Records 1982-2002
Older Women's League. Michigan Chapter.
9635 Bk 2
Michigan chapter of the national Older Women's league organization, founded in 1982 by Janet Good, with goal of improving the lives of older women by means of political advocacy. Records include correspondence, minutes and videotapes on history and goals of OWL, also includes some records of Farmington Hills chapter.
1 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was acquired on May 21, 1996, from Virginia White Nicoll (Donor No. 8482 ).
The collection is open for research.
The Older Women's League (OWL) is a national organization that seeks to improve the lot of older women within American society. OWL was formed in 1980 following the meeting of the White House Mini-Conference on Older Women. OWL Michigan and the Farmington Hills chapter, both founded in 1982 by Janet Good, were established to achieve the goal of improving the lives of older women by means of political advocacy. They also try to inform their members about issues such as legal rights, health concerns, and career options by arranging speakers, conferences, and workshops; by writing and distributing newsletters; and by holding regular meetings to discuss topics of concern. OWL Michigan's main activities are its annual meetings and conferences, to which all local Michigan chapters are invited. It also informs local chapters of regional and national OWL events, awards an OWL Michigan Role Model of the Year Award, and communicates with other groups that have similar interests in Michigan. The Farmington Hills chapter meets monthly, alternating board meetings with general meetings that feature speakers.
The folders are arranged for series; OWL Michigan, Farmington Hills Chapter, Royal Oak Chapter, and Videocassettes and in alphabetical order within series.
This collection primarily documents the history and activities of the Michigan state OWL organization (OWL Michigan) and the local chapter in Farmington Hills. The OWL records consist of four series, OWL Michigan, Farmington Hills Chapter, Royal Oak Chapter, and Videocassettes. Most of the records are self-explanatory.
Subjects:
Older Women's League (U.S.). Michigan Chapter.; Aged women--Michigan.; Farmington Hills (Mich.); Feminists--Michigan.; Feminism--Michigan.; Feminism--Michigan--Farmington Hills.; Women--Michigan--Societies and clubs.; Women's rights--Michigan.; Older Women's League (U.S.). Michigan Chapter.; Aged persons--Organizations--Michigan.; Feminism.; Aged persons--Political activity--Michigan.
Contributors:
Nicoll, Virginia White.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Videotapes.
- OWL Michigan
  The first series, OWL Michigan, includes a booklet of poetry entitled "Poetically Speaking: A Woman's Manifesto" written by Virginia Nicoll in 1991 and sold to raise money for the state organization. Permission to quote from this booklet must be granted by the author. The "Meeting minutes and agendas" file of this series contains several different types of minutes, including those of annual meetings, council meetings, and federation meetings.
  - History (Box 1)
  - Bylaws 1987-1990 (Box 1)
  - Conferences, speakers, and workshops 1984-1994 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1985-1993 (Box 1)
  - Feathering the Nest conference (Box 1)
  - Meeting minutes and agendas 1983-1999 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1982-1992 (Box 1)
    (includes photographs)
  - News clippings (Box 1)
  - Newsletter 1983-2002 (Box 1)
  - "Poetically Speaking," 1991 (Box 1)
  - Rosters 1985-1994 (Box 1)
  - Treasurer's reports 1986-1993 (Box 1)
- Farmington Hills Chapter
  In the second series, Farmington Hills Chapter, the researcher's attention is directed to the "News clippings" file. This file should not be overlooked; it contains not only detailed newspaper articles about the local chapter's speakers and activities but also memos and fliers that have been stapled to the corresponding clippings. To preserve the original order of the collection, these documents have been left together.
  - Annual reports 1982-1990 (Box 1)
  - Bylaws 1982-1990s (Box 1)
  - Calendars, conferences, events, etc. 1982-1992 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1982-1991 (Box 1)
  - Minutes
    - Chapter 1982-1999 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee/Board of Directors 1982-2000 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1981-2001, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - News clippings 1984-1991 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters 1984-1999 (Box 1)
  - Rosters 1982-1999 (Box 1)
  - Treasurer's report 1984-1992 (Box 1)
- Royal Oak Chapter
  The third series, Royal Oak Chapter, is quite small, consisting of a single folder of collected materials.
  - Miscellaneous 1984-1993 (Box 1)
- Videocassettes
  The fourth series, Videocassettes, contains segments of the talk show "Women on the Move," which feature Virginia Nicoll discussing OWL and its events and goals. It also includes tapes from OWL Michigan's 1989 and 1993 conferences and tapes of PBS documentaries featuring Virginia Nicoll.
  - "Women on the Move"
    (community access cable program, Farmington Hills, Mich. featuring Virginia Nicoll)
    - January 1989 (OWL history and goals) (Box 1)
    - October 1989 (OWL history and goals) (Box 1)
    - October 1991 (Nicoll's poetry book) (Box 1)
    - June 1993 (promoting, 1993 conference) (Box 1)
    - October 22, 1996, 60 minutes (Box 1)
      (OWL conference at Schoolcraft College, with Nancy Swanborg and Helen Thomas)
    - February 8, 2000 (Older women and health care), 30 minutes (Box 1)
  - OWL Michigan Conference
    (see also-program guides to the conferences in Owl Michigan/Conferences, speakers, and workshops)
    - 1989 "POW-er: Making the Personal Political", 2 tapes (Box 1)
    - October 1993 "From Broomsticks to Politics: Empowering Women" (Box 1)
  - PBS programs featuring Virginia Nicoll
    - "American Experience: After the Crash," January 7, 1991, 60 minutes (Box 1)
    - "The Great Depression," July 11, 1994, 60 minutes (Box 1)
  - "Women's Vote '96: The Deciding Vote", 10 minutes (Box 1)
    (9 public service announcements for Farmington Hills community access cable station, featuring voice-overs by Virginia Nicoll)